Praveen Kumar

System Engineer

Contact Details

- Call: +91 9430735066
- Email: praveen.thakurpt563@gmail. com
- <u>LinkedIn</u>
- GitHub

Technical Skills

- Azure & AWS Cloud
- Cloud Monitoring
- Python Coding
- Git & GitHub
- Linux Scripting
- Computer Networking
- Basic HTML, CSS
- SQL Query
- Office 365
- *Tool*: Jira, SQL Developer

Soft Skills

- Problem solving
- Effective Communication
- Open to Learning.
- Team player

Certification

- AZ-900 | Microsoft Azure Fundamentals
- CSS Essential Training-LinkedIn Learning.
- HTML Essential Training-LinkedIn Learning.

Awards and Achievements

- "Star of the Month Award" by TCS | Four Times
- "Prime Minister Scholarship" by PMO of India | Four times | 2016-2020.
- State Level Kabaddi Player.

Language

- English
- Hindi
- Maithili

Summary

Experienced Information Technology Analyst with a demonstrated history of working in the information technology and services industry. Skilled in HTML, CSS, python, Linux and Azure Cloud. Strong information technology professional with a Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.).

Experience

System Engineer | Tata Consultancy Services | April, 2023 - Current

- Implemented monitoring and logging via "AWS Cloudwatch" and "Azure Monitor" over different metrics.
- Automated the "ping/tnsping" test for "servers/Database instances" monitoring, using batch scrip and windows scheduler.
- Working as team lead and application manager, of GxP application.
- Migrated whole data from on application to another using SQL script on server
- Driven application enhancement, after identifying the issues in the application.

Assistant System Engineer | Tata Consultancy Services | April, 2021 - May, 2023

- License procurement and management, for Research application, by following industry standards.
- Installed upgrade, configure, maintained and administrated application hosted on Linux server.
- Audit system logs, password management, and user account maintenance.
- Installed upgrade, configure, maintained and administrated application hosted on windows server.
- Performed preventive maintenance on the Linux and Windows 2012 Servers.
- Identified and investigated system malfunctions/root cause analysis.
- Have a good understanding of ITIL concepts, worked with reporting tools such as SNOW
- End-to-End issue troubleshooting and documentation.

Education

- Bachelors of Engineering | 2016-2020 | Rustamji Institute of Engineering, Tekanpur, Gwalior, MP, India | 8.34 CGPA
- Higher Secondary | 2014-2016 | Kendriya Vidyalaya Chandrapura,
 Jharkhand | CBSE, Delhi, India | 80.20 Percentage